Cool.
Hello everyone.
Welcome to lecture 2 of CME 295.
So before we start, I
wanted to give you a heads
up about two logistical things.
So the first one is with
Shervine, we reviewed
the recording of lecture 1.
And we couldn't help but notice
that the audio was suboptimal.
So what we're doing
for this lecture
is to have another setup.
But then one issue
is my voice will not
be propagated in the room.
So I guess I have one question.
Can everyone hear me very
well, even from the back?
OK, cool.
Great.
So that's point number 1.
Point number 2 is
about the final exam.
So the final exam right
now has a placeholder date
for Wednesday, I think,
December the 10th.
But just a heads up
that we're trying
to see if there is a way to move
that to earlier in the week.
So we'll let when
that's finalized.
But for now, this is still TBD.
But we'll make sure
to let you know.
Cool.
So with that aside, let's
go into today's topic.
But before we do that, as
always, what we will do
is we'll just quickly recap what
we saw in the previous episodes.
So if you remember,
lecture 1 was all
about introducing the
concept of self-attention.
And if you remember,
what self-attention
is that each token is
attending to all other tokens
in the sequence through
this mechanism of attention.
So you have these notations
of queries, keys, and values.
So here the idea
is that the query
is going to ask which
other tokens are
most similar to itself by
comparing query and key.
And then once that's
done, basically we
will be taking the
associated value.
So we saw that the
self-attention mechanism can
be expressed with this
formula, so softmax
of query times key
transpose over square root
of dk times v. So I hope this
formula is familiar for you.
So just know that this
formula is highly optimized.
These are big matrix
multiplications, or hardware,
is very capable of doing, it's
very optimized in doing that.
And all of that to
say that we also
introduced the architecture
of the transformer, which
you can see on the right.
So here, if you
remember, the transformer
is composed of two
main components.
So the encoder on the
left side and the decoder
on the right side.
And the transformer
was initially
introduced in the context
of machine translation.
So you can think
of the left side
as processing the input
text in the source language,
say English.
And the right side is
responsible for decoding
the translation in a target
language, let's say in French.
And this multi-head
attention layer
is where the self-attention
mechanism happens.
And I remember there
was a lot of questions
regarding-- it's called
multi-head attention layer.
So there are several heads.
What does that correspond to?
So in the transformer paper,
which is the "Attention is All
You Need" paper, you
have this figure,
which actually represents
each of these heads.
And you can think of each head
as an opportunity for the model
to learn one way of projecting
the input into being
a query, a key, or a value.
So just being a bit more
clear, so for instance,
for the query and the key,
so this is like each head.
So the number of
these little boxes
is basically the
number of heads.
And to better visualize and
understand what this means,
I also wanted to
show I guess what
is being shown in the paper,
which is a way to interpret what
each of these heads do.
So we have this concept called
attention map, which basically
tries to represent the value
of each of these query,
dot product query.
So in this example,
what we're interested in
is to see which other token is
being most similar to token its.
And so what we do is we take
a look at the quantities,
the query that is
representing its,
dot product, all other keys.
And we look at what
are the keys are
leading to a high value of the
dot product query times key.
And when you do that,
basically what you see
or what the paper sees is
you have these two words, so
application and law, which
are highlighted as being
with the high-attention weight.
So attention weight
here being the dot
product of the query
its, and the key for each
of these tokens.
And I guess there is also
a way to interpret those.
And here you can see
that the tokens that
are being highlighted are
law and application, which
basically makes sense
because the token its
is referring to law.
So basically, the
model needs to learn
how to associate these words
with what happened before.
And its is also
referring to application,
which is also another way of
explaining why that is the case.
And so here what the
authors chose to do
was to show these
values as a function
of these different heads.
So for instance,
on the left side,
these are the
intensity for heads,
for let's say the first heads.
And then the second heads
shows that the intensity
is very high for law.
So basically, long story
short, these heads may learn,
I guess, different ways of
figuring out what words matters.
Yeah.
Great question.
So the question is, when we're
doing all these computations,
are they going through
different MLPs.
The answer is that we're going
to have different projection
matrices for each of them.
So we had this detailed example
that actually went through that
where each head is going
to have its own projection.
And in parallel, you're going
to have that computation that's
going to happen.
So each head is going to have
one result here, that is then
going to be concatenated and
then projected once again when
the output matrix.
So yeah, long story short,
it's highly parallelized.
And it's basically
just like projections.
And here you have some matrix
multiplication and softmax.
Does that make sense?
Cool.
Any other questions on this?
So I guess this is just a way to
illustrate the conversation we
had for lecture 1.
There was some questions
about these attention
heads, what they do.
And I guess looking
at the attention maps
is one way of making
sense of what they mean.
Cool.
With that, I highly recommend
that you read the transformers
paper, so "Attention
is All You Need."
So it's a very dense paper.
It's just a few pages long.
But I hope that what
you've seen in lecture 1,
you'll be able to digest
the content in a way that
will make sense to you.
Cool.
So with that, we're going to
start the actual meat of what
we're going to discuss today.
So surprisingly, this
transformer architecture,
which was introduced
in 2017, is actually
an architecture that has still
stayed relevant along the years.
And there are a few components
that have slightly changed.
And we're going to see
which ones they are.
So there are some
slight variations.
But overall, today's
models are, we're
going to see, all more or less
based on the initial transformer
architecture.
So we're going to try to
divide the class in two parts.
So the first one is
what I'm going to cover,
which is what are the parts
of the transformer that
are important and that
had some variation.
And in the second part, Shervine
is going to talk about, I guess,
the nomenclature
of today's models
and how they relate to
the original transformer.
Cool.
OK, so let's start with the
first important concept that's
in this architecture.
And this is the
position embedding.
So if you remember, here
we're letting tokens interact
with all other tokens
in a direct fashion.
So they have direct links.
But contrary to
things like RNNs,
where you have a
sequential dependency where
you process each
token one at a time,
here you're basically losing
this idea of a token being
processed before another one.
So you lose this
position information.
So as a result of that, we
need to somehow quantify tokens
at each position and try to
inject that information when
the transformer is
processing the inputs.
So how are we going to do that?
So the original
transformer paper authors,
they chose to have a
dedicated embedding.
And when I say dedicated, what
that means is each position
has one embedding.
So position 1 has one
embedding, position 2
has one embedding,
et cetera, et cetera.
And what they chose to do
is to add that embedding
to the input-token embedding.
So for instance, if I say a
cute teddy bear is reading,
which is position
number 1, representing
the token a, plus the embedding
representing the first position.
Yeah.
It's a great question.
So the question is, are
the position embeddings
learned or static?
Both, as in the authors
have tried both.
And we're going to see
what the second one is.
But I guess here let's
suppose that they are learned.
So what does that mean?
So that means that
basically you need to learn
embeddings for each position.
And the problem
with this approach
is that you're very
much dependent on what
is in your training set.
So for instance, like here,
if you have somehow a text
that always has something that
is happening at position number
2, your learned embeddings will
have that bias kind of learned.
So that's one
limitation of that.
Second limitation is you
can only learn positions up
to the max number of position
that is in your training set.
So let's suppose you train
your transformer on sequences
that are up to, let's
say, 512, let's say.
You can only learn position
embeddings up to that position.
Right?
Yeah.
So the question is, I guess,
how do you parameterize that?
So I guess what
you do is you have
a placeholder of a learnable
position embedding,
let's say between
position 1 and 512.
And basically, when
you do your training,
you're just letting
these weights
be learned through
the regular gradient
descent, all these things.
So yeah, so this is
like the first method.
But as I was mentioning,
it has its limitations,
because you can only learn
embeddings of positions
up to the max position that is
present in the training set.
So for instance, if you
have at inference time
a position that is
beyond the position that
was in the training set, well,
you have not learned that.
So you need to find a
way to infer the value.
So that's the second limitation.
But yeah, but on the pro
side, I guess you're just
letting your model learn.
And we've seen that
the gradient descent
does wonders when it comes to
just learning from the data.
So yeah.
And for these
reasons, these methods
was something that the authors
said that was performing well,
along with the second
method, which is different,
which is around
having an arbitrary
formula for each
dimension corresponding
to a position embedding.
And we're going to see that now.
So first method was you have
one embedding per position,
and you just learn that.
Second method is you have
one embedding per position,
but you're not
going to learn that.
You're going to have something
that is predetermined
that you're going to use.
And we're going to see that
what the authors choose
was a formulation
using sine and cosine.
So it can feel weird,
why did they choose this.
But we're going to see
why that makes sense.
So the idea here is for a
given position, let's say m,
have a vector of size d model.
So d needs to
match the dimension
of your token embeddings,
because of course you're
adding them.
And what you're going to
do is, for every index
you're going to compute the
corresponding value with respect
to these formulas.
So what are these formulas?
So it's basically sine
of something times m.
And we're going to see
what that something means.
And then the second one is
cosine of something times m.
So who remembers
trigonometry formulas?
Cool.
Everyone.
So before we go into that, let's
just simplify the notations.
Let's just assume that this
big quantity that you saw
is actually
something like omega.
So let's suppose it's omega
as a function of i times m.
And you note omega i
as being this quantity,
so 10,000 to the power
of minus 2i over d model.
Let's suppose you construct your
embeddings to have this way.
Then, I guess I want us to think
about why that would make sense.
Because if you think
about it, what you want
is to represent
positions in a way
that reflects the
following fact--
words that are
close together are
likely to be more relevant,
as opposed to words
that are further together.
So if you have two words that
are like just one position apart
versus 10,000 position apart,
what you want is that the one
that is one position apart is
more similar than the other one.
So let's see if the
formula makes sense.
So let's suppose you have two
position embeddings, so one
at position m and the
other one at position n.
And let's suppose you
compute in all the values
from this predetermined formula.
Well, it turns out,
if you remember
your trigonometry formulas,
so cosine of a minus b
is equal to cosine of a cosine
of b, plus sine a sine b.
Right?
Well, turns out that if you
express cosine of omega i,
factor of m minus n, this is
something that you obtain.
It's just the identity
that I mentioned.
Well, it just turns
out that this quantity
is just one component
that appears
when you do the dot product of
these two position embeddings.
Right?
Because basically
here, when you do
the dot product of position
m and position n, what you do
is you take the first
position, you multiply them,
then you plus the
second position,
you multiply them,
et cetera, et cetera.
And then you come here, it's
sign of this times sine of this,
plus cosine of this
times cosine of this,
which is just this quantity.
So at the end of the
day, what you realize
is that when you perform a dot
product of these embeddings,
you end up with a
sum of cosine that
are a function of the relative
distance between m and n.
Yep.
What do you mean by
pair, by the way?
Exactly, yeah.
So the question is, so
the closer they are,
the more similar they are.
So that's the intuition,
that basically
this way of formulating
the embeddings
is trying to approximate
or it's trying to mimic.
So with that, you basically
obtain a dot product
that is just a function of m
and n, the relative distance
between them, actually.
And just as a reminder, so why
do I care about the dot product?
Because if you remember,
in the embedding world
when we try to quantify
the similarity between two
embeddings, what
we do is typically
something that is involving
the dot product of these two.
So you typically have
the cosine similarity.
The cosine similarity
is just dot product
over the norm of each embedding.
So which is basically
a dot product.
Right?
So that's why we care
about the dot product.
And here we see,
great, it's a function
of the relative distance
between the two.
So in particular,
again, if you remember
your trigonometry
class, cosine of 0 is 1.
And the higher this
number, the lower the value
of cosine of this number.
Of course, it's periodic,
so what I'm saying
is not necessarily true.
Past pi, just goes
the other way.
But I guess what I'm trying
to say is for m equal to n,
you have basically a
sum of cosine of 0.
And it is the value at which
this quantity is maximum.
So when m is equal to n,
Which means basically if you're
looking at the position itself,
it's the most similar.
Basically, it matches
our intuition.
And so now when you plot the
values of the embeddings,
this is what you obtain.
So here in this
graph on the y-axis,
I'm basically representing
all the embeddings
for each of the, let's
say, 50 positions.
And on the x-axis,
it's basically
values along a given vector
across several dimensions
of a vector.
So if you take, let's
say, the first row,
you're looking at the
first or number 0 position,
depending on how you
index your vector.
And you're looking at all
the values of the position 0
embedding.
And so you see that
for low dimensions,
this value goes up and
down very frequently.
So it's more high frequency.
And when the dimension
is high, it basically
takes a lot of time for the
value to go up and down.
So it's basically
more low frequency.
So this relates to this omega i
that I mentioned, this omega i.
So omega i is very high
for low values of i,
which is the dimension.
And it's very low
for high values of i.
So this basically
just determines
how quickly your cosine
and sine basically vary.
Cool.
So this is what the
original authors have tried.
And basically what
they said, what they
noted was that
using these methods
leads to comparable results
compared to the learned one.
But here we have
a big advantage,
because it can extend to any
sequence length, not just
a sequence length that
you saw at training time.
And this is one of the
reasons why this may be
something that is preferable.
So yeah, this is the
intuition and this
is what the authors chose.
Now, fast forward to 2025.
I guess you may ask me,
are we still using that?
And the answer is kind of.
So we're still using this
idea of we want far--
I guess, tokens to be less
similar than closer tokens.
But we're not injecting the
embedding like they did.
And we're going to see why.
Because if you remember,
what you care about
is determining
how similar tokens
are in the self-attention
computation.
And where does the
self-attention computation
happen?
In the attention layer.
But here, what did I say?
I said, let's compute
these embeddings
and let's add them here.
But actually what we want is
to reflect this similarity
in the attention layer.
Do you have a question?
Yeah.
So in this first method, yes.
So the question is, is it
added to the input feature.
Yes.
Yes, just add.
Yeah, yeah.
But the problem is,
we mostly want these,
I guess, intuition to hold true
in the multi-head attention
layer.
So this is one of
the reasons why
people have tried different
variations, and in particular
have these position
embeddings intervene directly
in the attention layer,
as opposed to the input.
Because basically when
you do it at the input--
just here, fair, OK--
it's going to be
roughly something that
is going to go into
this attention layer,
but it's kind of indirect.
So what we want is to directly
do something about the attention
formula that would,
I guess, reflect
the fact that we want close
tokens to be more similar,
compared to further tokens.
And the way we do that
is, if you remember,
the self-attention layer is
basically the softmax of qk
transpose over square
root of d times v.
So what we want is to
add a little something
inside that softmax,
which is basically
where you quantify how similar
a token is to another token.
You want to add a
little something
to reflect the fact
that some tokens,
they're supposed to be more
similar compared to that token,
compared to others.
So there's a few
methods that have tried
to have some variation of that.
So for those of us who know
the T5 paper, what we're
going to see a little
bit later, they
have tried these
relative position bias
by learning the bias term,
which is in the formula above.
So what they did
was, let's suppose
you have a given distance
between the positions m and n.
So their idea was,
let's learn that.
Let's basically bucketize all
m minus n into some buckets.
And let's just have
the model learn
these quantities
that are then going
to be injected into softmax.
Yeah.
So the question is,
does that pose a problem
that the bias is
here with respect
to the probability at the end?
Because it has to sum to 1.
Well, you can do whatever
you want inside the softmax,
because the softmax is going
to normalize it anyways.
So you can think of the bias as
being something that is maybe
more negative for things
that are far apart, compared
to things that are
closer together.
So T5 says, let's learn them.
We have another message from,
I guess, this "Train Short,
Test Long" paper, which
introduced this method called
ALiBi.
ALiBi stands for Attention
with linear bias, I believe.
And what they did
was, say instead
of learning those
biases, let's actually
have a deterministic
formula, which
is as a function of the relative
difference between those two
positions.
And they said that.
So they had some results.
So all these papers, they always
compare based on one another
to see which one is, I
guess, more performant.
But the reality is is
that in today's models,
most models actually use another
kind of position embedding
method.
And we're going to see it now.
So this method
relies on rotating
the query and the key
vector by some angle.
And I guess you can think of
it as, you have your query,
you have your key, let's
suppose in a 2D space.
So what you're going to
do is rotate your query
by some angle that is a
function of its position.
And you're going to rotate the
key vector by some angle that is
a function of its position n.
And I guess how do you
do that, by the way?
I wasn't supposed
to show this thing.
So let's suppose you have
a vector, by the way.
And you want to
rotate that vector,
because I had the
answer on the slide.
But how would you go
about this, I guess,
for people who just want to
talk about this with intuition?
So who here has done, I don't
know, rotations in space?
Yeah.
That's correct, yeah.
Matrix multiplication.
And you're going to
use a quantity that's
called rotation matrix.
And the rotation matrix
is expressed as follows.
So it's basically a 2 by 2
matrix in the 2D plane that has
cosine of this angle,
minus sine of this angle,
sine of this angle,
cosine of this angle.
I'm looking at the time.
It's quite simple to
just show that it works,
but we may run out of time.
Do you want me to
quickly show you
that it's indeed a way
to rotate the vector?
OK.
So here as a reminder what we're
trying to show is that we can
use a matrix multiplication to
rotate a vector in 2D space.
So let's suppose we have
the following vector.
That is something that you can
quantify with two dimensions,
let's say x and y.
You can express your vector
in 2D space with this.
Right?
But I guess this, if you note,
are the norm of the vector,
and phi, the angle with
respect to the x-axis.
You can also write v
as R with vector cosine
of phi and sine of phi.
Right?
So if you multiply
the rotation matrix
with this phi, what
you're going to obtain
is some multiplication of cosine
minus sine, sine and cosine
of this and that.
And I will leave this
exercise for you.
But you can show that
rotation times this v
can be expressed as R of
cosine of theta plus phi,
and sine of theta plus phi.
So this is a quick proof.
So I'll just leave you the
multiplication of the rotation
matrix and v. But
you will obtain
these trigonometric
identities that will, I guess,
lead you to this formula.
This basically shows
that if you multiply
this matrix and this vector,
you're basically rotating
the vector by this angle.
Yeah.
So the question is, why
do you want to do this?
It's a great question.
It's my next slide.
So this is just a little intro.
So I guess here, just going
back to this method, what
we want to do is to quantify
the similarity between tokens,
and have close tokens
be more similar compared
to tokens that are more afar.
So the problem that we had
with the previous methods was--
so in the first method,
this learned embedding,
you always had this
overfitting issue.
Because basically when
you learn these biases,
it always depends on which
training set you have.
So maybe your data set is
in a way that, let's say,
tokens that are close are
similar, but in a different way
compared to what you
see at inference time.
And this ALiBi method, it didn't
have that learnable component,
but it was quite
restrictive, because it's
a very simple formula after all,
just the relative difference
between n and m.
So I guess people have tried
different ways of coming up
with something that tells you
that, I guess, an embedding that
reflects the fact that you want
further positions to be less
similar than closer ones.
So in this method,
we're going back
to the sine and
cosine world from what
the author had proposed.
And think about
similarity from the lens
of cosine and sine functions.
So this is a little intro.
And their method is called RoPE.
So I'm not sure if
you've heard of it.
So it stands for Rotary
Position Embeddings.
And we're going to see
that this method-- so
why do we care
about this method?
So this method has
two great things.
So the first one is that if you
rotate the query and the key,
you will end up
with a quantity that
will be a function of
the relative distance
between the two.
That's going to be
very nice, and that's
why I wrote this thing
on the blackboard.
Not sure if you can
see, by the way,
but we won't have time to go
into the mathematical detail.
But if you want to just
express these things at home,
this is just the foundation.
And so in particular, if you
remember your attention formula,
so you have query
times key transpose.
So if you rotate the
query by an angle m
and the key by an angle n,
what you're going to end up
is a formula that has the
rotation matrix of angle theta
and, I guess, n minus m.
And this is great
because this is
a function of the relative
distance between these two
positions.
OK, so why do I talk
about this in detail?
Well, it turns out that
most models these days,
they use RoPE, which
is why it's important.
And I would say another thing,
it's maybe a little bit hard
to get the intuition
as to why that works.
But hopefully, the explanation
that I gave regarding the sine
and cosine at the very
beginning can help you just
build that intuition.
And speaking of
that, it turns out
that the upper bound of
the attention weight given
by the query and the
key is such that we
observe a long-term decay.
Meaning that as n
minus m is large,
we do see the upper bound
that gets smaller and smaller.
Well, you see these
little oscillations,
it's not perfect either.
But we do have
some mathematical,
I guess, results as to
just the upper bounds
decaying over the long-term.
Cool.
Any questions on this?
Yeah, yeah.
Exactly, yeah.
So the question is
the relative distance
is captured in the
rotation matrix--
and yes, yes.
Oh, yeah.
It's a great question.
So the question
is, what is theta?
So theta is actually fixed.
So do you remember this omega
that I talked about here?
Here.
So it's basically some
function of i and d.
I actually pass
it quite quickly.
But what I showed you
is in the 2D space.
But here we're in a
d-dimensional space,
which is greater than 2.
So I glossed it very quickly.
But the way you extend this
method is by having these 2D
space by block.
But then the theta is a
function of typically something
that you fix, but a function
of i, which is the dimension.
It's basically between
1 and d over 2.
It's a function of that, and
it's a function of d as well.
You will see this theta as being
roughly equal to omega i, just
this one, more or
less, more or less.
Sorry?
Oh, so the question is, so
that it has the same dimension
as the latent dimension?
So, well, here you have
a product of matrices.
So you need to have
the dimensions match.
So I guess your answer-- yeah.
Does that make sense?
I'll take that as a yes.
So I spent a bunch
of time on this,
because I think this is
actually quite important.
A lot of models use this.
And yeah, I guess the
intuition is not super obvious.
So I hope this was helpful.
So this was position embeddings.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, so the question is about,
how do you obtain this curve?
So this is actually a
curve that I believe
is shown mathematically.
So it's kind of complicated.
We're not going to
write down the formula.
But if you're interested,
so in this paper,
in the RoFormer paper,
there's an appendix
where they show
mathematically that it is
upper bounded by some quantity.
And this is what
this is showing.
Yeah, great question.
Cool.
So, position
embeddings is one part
of the transformer that
has changed a little bit.
And we've seen how
that changed, and why.
So now we're going to
see another component
of the transformer that has
also a little bit changed.
And that component is
the layer normalization.
So if you remember, the
transformer architecture,
which is composed,
again, of encoder,
decoder, and then you have
the components inside.
So you have these boxes
that say add and norm.
So what do they mean?
So basically, here, what we do
is we take the input, as well as
the output of this sublayer.
We add them together,
and then we normalize.
So this is a little trick
that the authors do.
And it is shown in practice to
improve convergence and just
make the convergence be quicker.
So the idea is as follows--
if you have a vector, sometimes
the components of the vector
can be super large, sometimes
they can be super small.
The idea here is to normalize
the components of your vector
within some range,
some normalized range.
So the way you're going
to do that is you're
going to take your vector,
and then subtract it
by the computed mean,
which is basically
the sum of its components,
and normalize it by basically
its standard deviation.
And what you're
going to do is you're
going to learn two quantities--
one, gamma, which is going
to be the rescaling factor,
and then beta, which is another
term as well that you learn.
And you're going to let
these two quantities be
learned by your model.
And so in practice, as I
mentioned, so what this does
is it helps with
training stability
and with convergence time.
So this was a technique that was
used in the original transformer
paper.
I just want to call
out that there has
been some changes since then.
So we went from
normalizing the input
plus the output of the sublayer,
to having a sum of the input
and the sublayer of
the normalized input.
So in other words,
what we've done
is to change where the
normalization is located.
So here in the
transformer paper,
it was what we now call
a post-norm version.
And nowadays, we use
a pre-norm version,
which basically consists of
having the LayerNorm right
before the vector goes
into the sublayer.
And sublayer here can be either
the attention layer or the FFN.
But not only that, there
is also another change.
So nowadays, people, they
do not use LayerNorm.
They use something
else called RMSNorm--
RMS, Root Mean
Square, Normalization,
which is basically a variation
of what you've seen before.
So instead of computing this,
basically what people do
is they just normalize
x by the root
mean square of the
components of x,
and they learn
gamma, only gamma.
So why do they do that?
Basically, they show that
the convergence properties,
they're basically comparable.
But here you have fewer
parameters to learn.
So it's basically quicker.
Yeah.
Good question.
So the question is, what is the
intuition behind normalizing?
So the intuition is that,
if you look at your model,
you have several layers.
In some layers your vector--
your activation, to
be more precise--
so do you know the
vector that you
see that goes from here to here
is basically called activation.
Sometimes the activation
has extreme values
in one part of its component,
sometimes in another part.
And the model is
typically having
trouble in learning the
weights in each of these layers
if these activations,
they vary too much.
So the idea is to bring the
values of the components
of the activation to
some range that is not
too far off in some direction.
So in case you're
interested, there
is this key word,
internal covariate shift,
which is basically the term
that is given to the phenomenon
that I'm describing here.
So yeah, that's the intuition.
Yeah.
Oh, great, great question.
So question is, what is
the difference between this
and batch normalization?
So batch normalization
is normalization
across the other
dimension, which
is the dimension of the batch.
So let's suppose you
have a bunch of vectors.
What you do is you normalize
each component with respect
to all the other components
for the same dimension,
but of the other vectors.
So you can think of it as just
another way of normalizing.
But that being
said, when it comes
to these
transformer-based models,
typically people use
LayerNorm, probably
because empirically
it works better.
But also because
BatchNorm, you're
basically also
dependent on the batch.
And it can introduce, I guess,
differences between training
and then inference.
So that's basically
the reason why.
Cool, great.
So we've seen
position embeddings.
We've seen layer normalization.
So now we're going to see
a third important component
of the transformer,
which is the attention.
And in particular, I
guess there is something
I've not really emphasized.
But when you do
self-attention, you're
basically letting every token
interact with all other tokens.
So when you look at,
let's, say a matrix
that shows all the
interactions, so you
have n, the sequence length.
And the sequence
length, you basically
have o of n squared complexity,
which is a lot, especially
as n grows longer.
So people have tried to
approximate this o of n squared
into something that is a
little bit more tractable,
but does not lose
the performance.
So there is this paper in 2020
that came out, "LongFormer."
So what it did was just
try different versions
of the attention by restricting
the window at which it operates.
So here, instead of letting each
token interact with everyone,
each token only interacts
with its neighborhood.
Yeah.
Oh, again, a great question.
So question is, do you do that
after the attention matrix
computation?
You mean the softmax,
right, softmax?
So you raise a
great point, which
is, if you do the
softmax of everything,
why would you do this?
So in practice there is a
bunch of implementations
that does a clever--
so it's called tiling--
a bunch of clever
operations that
do not involve this
huge matrix operation
that you see in the softmax.
Again, I guess, like against the
softmax of qk transpose over d.
You're not going to
compute the whole thing.
You're going to have
some cleverness in how
you compute that, basically.
Yeah, so the question is,
can it be something that's
comparable to convolutions?
And we're going to
see that in a second.
But you have some similarities
with the vision world.
And we're going to
see that in a second.
Cool.
So nowadays when you have local
attention like this, like this,
people use the term
sliding window attention.
So when they use
that term, they mean
this, which is basically just
restricting the attention
to neighboring tokens.
And nowadays what people
do is in some layers
they will have local attention.
In some others, they will
have global attention.
And they interleave
these layers.
So depending on the
model, they typically
try different combinations.
So there's not a set recipe.
But it's typically something
that is used nowadays.
So the window here, I mean,
for, illustrative, purposes,
the window is super
small in my illustration.
But I guess nowadays
with the sequence lengths
that can be very big, you can
think of this window as being,
o of several, thousands.
And just to give
you another example.
So back to the convolution
comparison that you mentioned.
So you have some architectures.
And here I'm going to take
the example of a mistral that
has these sliding window
attention at every layer.
But then when you
think about it,
the token here can attend
up to the token here,
but then the token
here can attend up
to the token here,
et cetera, et cetera.
So I guess, if you
think about it,
it's similar to the
idea of the receptive
field in computer vision.
So I'm not sure if you're
familiar or from the computer
vision world.
But if you are, what this
means is just taking one token
and trying to think
what other tokens has
this token effectively
interacted with,
which is basically the question
that people also sometimes ask.
When they do
convolution, they're
like, OK, so this value,
what are the values
did it actually see?
So you can also
think it this way.
OK, so first
variation is, instead
of doing the full
n by n attention,
people sometimes
do local attention.
The second variation that
is orthogonal to all of this
is to not have one
projection matrix per head,
but to share projection
matrices across heads.
So here the idea is you
have, let's say, h heads.
The idea is you're going to
have some number of projection
matrices for the query.
But then what you're
going to do is
to group the projection matrices
for the key and the value
that you're going to share
across several heads.
Now you may ask, why do you
share projection matrices
for the keys and the values,
but not for the queries?
Is this the question
that you're wondering?
Well here, I guess, people
do things to just try out
if something works or not.
I guess here you can
intuitively think
that the query is basically
wondering if something
is similar to another thing.
So I guess you can ask yourself
this question in different ways.
So it may make sense
to keep that diversity.
But one of the core reasons why
we choose to group projection
matrices for the
keys and the values
and not the query is
because, when you decode,
you perform attention between
the current word and all
the words before.
So in other words, every
time you generate a new word,
you're going to attend that
word to all the words before.
So the keys and the values,
they're going to come up a lot.
So every time you want
to decode something,
you need to attend to all
other things, again and again.
So we're going to
see in, I think,
next, lecture there's
something called
the KV cache, which basically
saves the values of the keys
and values.
And one thing that we
want is for that cache
to not become too big.
So if you share projection
matrices across heads,
just allows you to save
a little bit of space,
a little bit of memory.
That's the why.
Does that roughly make sense?
OK, cool.
So speaking of that, there are
some variations as to, I guess,
just how many projection
matrices to share.
So you have the
extreme example where
all h heads, they all
share the same projection
matrices for v and k.
And in that case,
this method is called
MQA, Multi-Query Attention.
You have the in-between
case where you share g,
where g is the number of groups
g projection matrices for v
and k.
And then you have groups of
size, let's say, h over g.
So this one is called
Group Query Attention, GQA.
And then you have the case
that you are very familiar
with from the
transformer, which is
every head has its own query
projection, key projection,
and value projection matrices.
And this is the standard,
multi-head attention.
Cool.
So I'm, going to just take a
pause to see if what I mentioned
makes sense.
I'm going to soon
transition it to Shervine.
But before I do, I just want to
make sure that what I discussed
is making sense, roughly.
Yeah.
So the question is,
do we apply this
to self-attention
and cross-attention?
I don't want to spoil the show.
So I'm going to talk
about something later on.
But where is my trans?
So if you take a look at the
transformer architecture,
we're going to see soon
that what we care about most
is what is in the decoder,
because we actually
forego of the encoder
in nowadays' models.
We have not seen this yet,
but I'm just telling you.
And so this typically
comes into play
for the masked self-attention
in the decoder.
But this technique can be
applied in all attention layers.
But I guess what
I'm telling you is
modern LLMs, their decoder only
models which basically only
have the decoder part
of the transformer.
We're going to see
this in a second, which
is the masked self-attention.
So I'm not going to say
too much because Shervine
is going to cover that.
But yeah, just a quick peek
of what we're going to see.
Cool, yeah.
Yeah.
Great question.
So the question is, when do you
know which one you should use?
I would say the choice is
always driven by a few factors.
One is how well it performs.
Second is how much do you care
about things like latency costs.
And so it really depends
how big is your model,
how much you want to save
on, let's say, compute,
how is your input
length, for instance
if you have a
shorter input length.
So here what we want
to do is to avoid
having to do all these things
for the whole o of n squared
thing.
So I guess all of
these come into play.
So I would say it's
not straightforward as
to what the answer should be.
But I would say a
lot of recent models,
they tend to share
projection matrices.
So typically, I would say
GQA is what you would see.
But it's not necessarily
the case for all models.
Cool.
We're running out of time.
So I'm going to have Shervine
here for the second part.
Thank you.
OK, great.
Thank you, Afshine.
So we're going to continue this
lecture with some deeper dive
into the kinds of
models that we have
in the transformer landscape.
And then we're going
to do a deep dive
into one specific
architecture that
is very useful for
classification settings.
So first, we're going to
come back to the architecture
that we saw together
last time, so
this traditional
encoder/decoder architecture
where you have both components.
And so you have the original
transformer paper from 2017
that had this architecture.
But also later on, you
see more architectures
that built on top of it.
So here we talk about
the T5 family of models.
So T5 is a paper that's an
abbreviation of multiple Ts.
So the first one is transfer,
and then it's text-to-text,
transformers.
So this is where the
T5 naming comes from.
And then it's derived
into multiple versions.
So the T5 is like
the vanilla paper.
And then it had mT5.
m stands for
multilingual where there
was some more work on the
data it was trained on,
as well as the vocabulary
that it was computed over.
And then you have
ByT5, which is some
of tokenizer-free method of
all of this where you forego
of the fact of tokenizing.
And instead of
that, you basically
operate at the byte level.
So By is like byte.
And basically, you
have a vocabulary size
that is much smaller.
So instead of
having an o of 30k,
you have 2 to the power of 8.
So a byte is 8 bits.
And then you can represent
every character into bytes.
So that's what they do.
OK, great.
And then one thing
I want to mention
regarding the T5 family is that
the objective function changes
a bit with what the
original transformer did.
So the original transformer
did next token prediction
for the training task.
But the T5 family,
what they did is
that they operated on the
so-called span corruption task.
So basically you would
have your sentence
as an input to the encoder.
And instead of putting
everything to the encoder,
you would leave blanks.
And this is what we
call span corruption.
And then the span
corruption could be
one or multiple tokens missing.
So if I want to give an
example, so for example,
my teddy bear is
cute and reading.
So you could have my teddy bear
span corrupted, and is reading.
So that could be one
potential encoder input.
And then you could
have up to n--
I mean, n is the
parameterization
of the number of spans
that are corrupted.
So you would have
n such tokens here.
And then the T5 families
calls them sentinel tokens.
So if you see
sentinel tokens, they
represent a span of
corrupted tokens.
So you have them
here in the encoder.
And then the decoder's
work is to find
each of these spans in series.
So you start with a
token that denotes
the first corrupted span.
And then you start
the decoding process
until it hits a prediction that
predicts the next sentinel token
up to the n plus 1, 1, where
the tokens that are decoded
between two consecutive
sentinel tokens
corresponds to the corrupted
spans that are recovered.
So these parentheses
is basically
a shift from the next token
prediction objective function.
Yep.
Yeah.
So the question is, can you
elaborate with the decoding
process?
So what you said regarding the
reconstruction is exactly right.
So you have sentinel tokens
that denote some missing text.
So what you want to decode
is that missing text.
So the decoder output
will be exactly
like each span reconstructed.
And then if you want to
know how training works,
you do a teacher-forcing
mechanism
where you input
everything in the decoder,
and then try to reconstruct
everything at once.
So any other questions?
Great.
And then now we're going
to talk about another class
of transformers where basically
you have this encoder/decoder
structure, where you just forget
about the decoder and then just
deal with the encoder.
So you might tell me, OK, hey,
you cannot do generation with
this.
And then I would respond to you,
yes, that's exactly the point.
So it has encoder
representations
that can be used for
tasks that might be more
geared towards classification.
So sentiment extraction,
token classification,
all of these things that used to
be done with specific language
models, they can be
done with the encoder
part of the transformer.
And we're going to
dive deeper a bit later
into a three-key
encoder only models.
So BERT, which is
like the central one,
I would say in this
landscape, and then
two other architectures,
DistilBERT and RoBERTa,
that are investigating
on axis of improvements.
So it's going to be good to see.
So OK, great.
And then there is
one last class.
So as Afshine just
mentioned, two days
LLMs, they remove the
encoder part altogether.
And then when you
have no encoder,
you don't have your
encoder embeddings
at the end of your
stacked encoders
that could be fed to
the cross-attention.
So this module
disappears altogether.
So each decoder
that is stacked just
has masked self-attention
and an FFN as part of it.
And yeah, that's
basically something
that has caught up since then.
Because when you look at
the popularity of each
of these models,
so you used to have
these transformer-like
architecture that was popular
towards the beginning, where
the main hypothesis was
that the encoder part is
very useful for getting
to the decoder's representation.
But as time went,
people realized
that your compute budget
could be best invested
in the decoder only.
And then there has been more
investment into the kind
of tasks that is, I would
say, easiest to scale up
and generalize--
next-word prediction--
as opposed to the task
I just mentioned for T5,
which might be more bespoke.
So you need to corrupt things.
So it's more complex.
Whereas next-word
prediction is, I would say,
the simplest thing you can do.
And it proved to be
wonders and well-aligned
with the task of being a
helpful kind of chatbot,
which is like two days'
applications mainly.
And then the decoder-only
architectures-- so I'm not
going to talk about them today.
But it's going to be the central
part of the next lectures
when we're going to talk
about LLMs more and more.
OK, awesome.
So now we can dive
deep, as promised,
into encoder-only
architectures and with BERT.
So first we're going to start
by seeing what does BERT mean.
So BERT, it's an acronym that
denotes Bidirectional Encoder
Representations
from Transformers.
And we're going to
see together how
does each section of this
acronym, what does it
correspond to?
So let's just start
with the encoder part,
which is the easiest to grasp.
So as we said, we just
dropped the decoder.
So this encoder from
transformer is basically
exactly what it means.
Now on the other part, so why do
we talk about bidirectionality?
So it's a way, so the
paper's result is remarkable,
because we are able
from a given input
to get output representations
that have attended to everything
for each token.
And this is the case.
Because since we only
have the encoder,
we have this
self-attention layer
that truly attends
to every other token.
And this is in contrast with
the masked self-attention
that you have where we said that
the mask is making the attention
mechanism causal.
So every token can attend
to itself and to the tokens
before it.
And this is, by
the way, something
that the authors discuss
a lot in the paper,
saying that GPT came out, GPT
they're not truly bidirectional.
And then these encodings that
can be used for classification
tasks, they truly are.
Any questions?
Yep.
Yep, that's right.
So the question is, when
you don't have the mask,
each token can
attend to each other.
That's exactly right.
And then the mask
is exactly there
to prevent links from tokens
to those that come after them.
Yeah.
OK, great.
So I just want to put
this paper in context.
And the field of NLP
was booming back then.
So you had another
landmark paper
that same year, which
was called ELMo,
so Embeddings from
Language Models.
And I would say that
the timing of that paper
was a bit unfortunate,
because it truly
had new insights
of also building
bidirectional representations.
But it just turns out
that it came the same year
as the transformer, as the kind
of transformer-based same line
of work.
So it got a bit masked by it.
So ELMo, just to
give the main lines,
it was based on a
bidirectional LSTM
where you had
multiple layers, each
stacked on top of each other.
And basically you
were able to build
a bidirectional
representation for each word,
thanks to this architecture.
And so why didn't it
become as popular as BERT?
It's because you had
the same downsides
as the previous models,
where basically it's
hard to scale because
of this recurrence.
And I think a lot of you, when
you think about ELMo and BERT,
you don't think about
these papers at first,
because they are characters
in Sesame Street.
And I grew up in a
place where I did not
know about Sesame Street.
So for me, ELMo and BERT
is like paper names.
But it might be what
represents to you at first.
So I thought that
was quite funny.
And then researchers, they
are generally quite playful.
They try to fit their
acronyms into themes.
So if you look at paper names,
you will get entertained.
OK, great.
So to dive deeper
into what I mentioned
to be the goal of
encoder-only models,
so you have your set
of tokens as input.
And the goal here
is to perform tasks
that might be
focused on projecting
some representation somewhere,
so typically classification
tasks.
And here, the way BERT
works is very specific.
So you have two kinds
of tokens that you
will see are structural here.
So you have first the CLS token,
which stands for classification.
And it's basically
a placeholder token
that is put at the beginning
of the sequence that will then,
at the end of the
whole attention
and then projection and the
whole encoder mechanism,
be projected into an
embedding that we can then
use for classification.
So CLS is just some
kind of placeholder
that will carry the
bidirectional information
of your whole input.
And another token that might be
useful to see is this SEP token.
So it's like separator.
And then you will
see very soon we're
going to see the objective
functions that it operates on.
It aims at separating
two sentences.
Yeah.
So this is the very high level.
And then so one thing
that is very interesting
to see with this model is
that you have this concept
of multi-stage training.
So you don't train
the model in one shot.
You do it in multiple stages.
So the first stage is
aimed at being aligned
with the task of interest.
And so this is what
we call pre-training.
And this pre-training,
we will see in detail,
is done with two objective
functions that are respectively
MLM and NSP.
So MLM stands for
Masked Language Model.
And NSP is the Next
Sentence Prediction.
So masked language
model, it's a way
for the model to learn
the internal structure
of the inputs.
And then NSP, it
might be seen as a way
to see if the ordering
of sentences makes sense.
So we're going to go a
bit deeper into each,
but it's a combination
of objective function
that the authors assumed
to be helpful for learning
general embeddings
of high quality.
OK.
So the second thing
that I want to mention
is that, once you
have all of this,
you have a further stage where
you keep the embeddings that you
have learned.
And then you attach to it some
other network, like typically
a linear projection,
to then fine tune
the embeddings that you have
learned into some target task.
So this is what we
call fine tuning.
Yep.
So yeah.
So the question is, do we still
have just an encoder here?
Because a next-sentence
prediction
could be seen as a decoder task.
So actually I'm going
to go in detail.
The next-sentence
prediction task
is actually us putting two
sentences, one after the other,
and predicting whether
they are truly consecutive.
So it's a classification task.
Yeah, great point.
And yeah, we're going to see
that in detail very soon.
So before we see
that in detail, I'm
going to discuss the pros and
cons that this method usually
has.
So regarding on the pro side,
this pre-training mechanism
can be done on fairly
unlabeled data.
So you still have this
next-sentence prediction task.
But this is something
that you control,
because you know which
sentences follow each other.
So it's something that you
know it's self-supervised.
And the masked language
model task, we're
going to see how it consists.
But it's also something
that is unsupervised.
So this is a very
interesting way
to learn interesting embeddings
out of unlabeled data.
And then in practice
is that we see
that these unlabeled data leads
to helpful representations being
learned.
And then you need very little
data to build on top of it.
So at the fine tuning
stage, you just
start from these
very nice embeddings
that you have learned, and you
just have a few weights to tune.
And then this usually leads
to a performance that exceeds
state of the art back then.
And then regarding
the downsides,
we have of course all
the text generation
tasks that are out of reach
because we don't have a decoder.
And also, we can see these
two stage process and the fact
that we need to
further tune embeddings
as something that
can be over hurdled.
So it might be, when you
compare this kind of methodology
with respect to more traditional
methods, that can be one shot.
This could be seen
as a downside.
OK, great.
And I have some names
regarding variants here.
We're going to dive deep into
two of them a bit later on.
OK.
So I want us to focus on
the original transformer.
And we're going to go step by
step into what happened to it,
and then how we get
the BERT architecture.
So this is what we had in the
original transformer paper
that we saw last week.
And what BERT did is extract
the encoder part of it
and attach basically these new
objective functions that I just
mentioned, alongside some
new set of tricks when it
comes to representing tokens.
So I think we're going to
go through them one by one.
So first of all,
one interesting note
is that it uses a specific
tokenizer called WordPiece.
So you can see it
as a tokenizer that
learns on your training set,
based on merge rules that
maximize the likelihood.
So basically, you have
some huge training set,
and you train a tokenizer that
merges atomic tokens together
to build your target vocabulary.
And some order of magnitude,
I mentioned o of 30k.
So it's typically, I
think this is the size
that they chose in this paper.
And in general, like vocabulary
sizes in these sorts of paper
are in the order of magnitude
of 10 to the power of 4,
10 to the power of 5, except
for our token-free method
that we saw, like ByT5,
which is like this very
restricted set of tokens, like 2
to the power of 8, which is 256.
Apart from this specific
case, you always
have this order of magnitude.
And basically, we are going
to make use of the tokens
that I mentioned.
Like at the beginning,
so you have the CLS token
that is going to carry the
bidirectional representation
of all your sequence.
And then you have SEP
tokens to separate
the two sentences towards the
next-sentence prediction task.
And there is something that I
haven't talked about just yet.
So I think maybe we
can talk about it
at the time of the deep dive.
So in order to have this
masked language model task,
so of course you need
to mask some tokens.
So we're going to see the
technique that is basically
applying these sorts of mask and
where and at which frequency.
And we're going to see with
respect to the output what
is going to be our task based
on the resulting representation.
So I'm just going to
pass quickly on it here,
but we're going to
come back very soon.
OK, great.
So one big piece of news
regarding your input
embeddings--
so what stays the same?
So you still have these
huge dictionary lookup
of embeddings for each token
that you're going to learn.
And you're going to additively
add the positional encoding
that we saw at last lecture.
And Afshine talked about
earlier in this lecture,
which can either be
hard-coded or learned.
I think the authors here just
used a hard-coded version here,
but I'm not too sure.
But it's roughly the
same performance usually.
But there is something new.
There is the introduction
of a new kind
of encoding called segment
encoding that is going to still
be additively added to tokens,
with the exception that we just
have two possible
encodings there.
So you have segment A that
represents the first sentence,
and then segment B that
represents the second sentence.
And it's supposed to
help with the NSP task
to represent what could be
features that can helpfully
represent a sentence that
precedes another one.
So at least that
was the hypothesis
admitted by the authors.
We're going to see it has
been challenged later on.
But this is one of
the key concepts
that was introduced here.
Any questions so far?
Yep.
Yep, so a great point.
So the question is, what does
segment encoding do at all?
So it's basically
something that is learned.
So you have two
indices, two basically
embeddings that you can learn.
You just additively
add them, segment
A for tokens in the first
part of the sentence,
and then segment B
in the second part.
And you just learn it
with gradient descent.
So you do nothing with it.
I think there was
another question here?
Yeah.
That's right.
So the question is, is every
token in the same sentence
going to have the
same segment encoding?
Yes, yeah.
OK, awesome.
So I'm seeing I might need
to speed up a tiny bit.
So yeah, the second thing
that I want to highlight here
is that we take the encoder
part of the transformer.
And nothing new here.
It's just the same.
We have self-attention,
followed by these FFN.
So this is where you're going
to get your bidirectional nature
of your encodings.
And then basically
we're assuming
that training both
MLM and NSP on it
is going to help us
learn helpful projection
matrices in this encoder
that can be suited
for any classification task.
OK, great.
And as promised, I talked
about detailing more about what
this MLM task was going to do.
So when you look at
the input, you're
going to basically have
your input sentence,
and replace at
random some tokens.
So it will be replaced
either with the token mask.
So it's in 80% of the time.
In 10% of the time,
the tokens selected
for this MLM objective
function are not
going to be replaced at all.
So we're just saying,
it's the same token,
just predict the same token.
And then 10% of the
time, it's going
to be changed to some
random other word.
So at the end of it,
you have the subset
of tokens you're going to
perform your MLM task on.
And then this is
how it's composed.
OK, great.
And so basically
the intuition here
is that when you want to
predict what a token is,
you need to know
about its context.
So we're going to
force the model
to learn about what
surrounds it, left and right.
So this is the bidirectional
property of this architecture
put into action.
OK, great.
And now we're going to talk
about the next-sentence
prediction task where
basically the process here
is to select two sentences
from a given corpus,
and then present them side by
side in order 50% of the time,
and in some random order
the other part of the time.
And the goal is for
some classification head
on top of the CLS token to
determine whether A and B are
consecutive.
So that's all it does.
And so the assumption
is that it also helps
learn some useful embeddings.
OK, great.
And here I'm going to
present the notation that
is used in the paper.
So the paper is something
I recommend reading.
It's a very nice read, alongside
the "Attention is All You Need."
I would say it's
a landmark paper.
I think it has a 170k citations,
something really impressive.
And basically what we called
n in the original transformer
paper is now called L. H,
that was called d model,
is the dimension
of our embeddings.
And A is the number
of attention heads,
which was called the little h.
So here I'm just showing these
new notations for information,
just to give you the mapping.
But of course,
together with Afshine,
we're going to stay consistent
with the original notations we
had, so just like
for information.
And one interesting
note is that you
will see that the
BERT model, when
you look at some repository of
models such as Hugging Face,
so usually it's given
in several versions.
So you will see sometimes
like case, uncased.
So this denotes what
kind of preprocessing
was done to the data,
whether you only
have lowercase words in there
or whether casing matters.
So based on your
task of interest,
it might be one thing
you want to choose from.
OK, great.
And I give some
orders of magnitude
from the paper on what values
were chosen for each of these.
So if I remember
correctly, I think
the original transformer had 12
stacked encoders and decoders.
So I think some numbers
here were taken from there.
So yeah, order of magnitude
is 100 million parameters.
Any questions so far?
OK, great.
And then now we're going to
talk about the fine-tuning stage
where the goal is
to basically take
whatever we have learned
at pre-training stage,
and then freeze those weights.
And instead of training
again on those same weights,
you have some
classification linear layer
that is put on top of
either the CLS token
or on top of tokens of interest.
And you're going to learn about
the linear embeddings there.
So you're going to have
some classification task.
So you could either freeze
all these pre-trained weights
and just train on
these small weights.
Or you can just retrain
the whole thing.
I think there is multiple
classification schemes.
And some of it will be
influenced by your willingness
to retrain a lot of
the network and how
different the classification
task is with respect
to the original
pre-training task.
OK, great.
And then just to give
some examples of what
could be fine-tuning tasks
for tasks of interest,
you can have a
sentiment extraction
where you build a classification
layer on top of the CLS token.
And we give some other
example question answering
where basically you
are given some input.
And the goal of the model is
to detect beginning and end
spans of the response.
So it's basically some
objective function
that is at the token level.
OK, great.
So now I propose that
we do some deep dive
into one specific example.
Our favorite example, this
teddy bear is so cute.
Let's just see how
BERT works in practice.
So basically what you would
do in an uncased setting
is take the sentence,
pre-process it, just
put everything lowercase.
Then you apply the
WordPiece algorithm
on whatever tokenization
mechanism that your tokenizer
has learned.
So for example here, apparently
it had all these merge rules.
So this is the tokens that
appear in the vocabulary.
And then as I promised, we add
the CLS token at the beginning.
And then we add the SEP token.
And you also have
this PAD tokens
that are basically used to fill
out the sequence until the end.
Because when you train,
you train by batch,
and then batches are
composed of matrices
that have a fixed length.
Yeah.
So let's just have
this deep dive a bit
the same as what we had in the
transformer deep dive last time.
So you have the embeddings
that are learned.
So it's some huge lookup table
between the index of each token
and the learned representation.
So you add to it the position
embedding of the token.
And something that's new here--
the segment embedding.
So exactly as we said,
it's an embedding
that is added to each token.
And the same embedding is
added to the same tokens.
So all the tokens have
the same segment A.
Then some other embedding B
is added to all the tokens
of the segment B. OK, great.
So now you have, similarly
as the transformer,
something that is position-aware
and context-aware--
so not context-aware just
yet, but segment-aware here.
OK, great.
And basically it goes through
this encoder architecture.
And then at the end
of it, for the case
of sentiment
extraction, we do not
care about the
embeddings that are
corresponding to each token
that is not the CLS token.
Because what we care about is
the output embedding of the CLS
token, where we
plug a linear layer
that will learn some
classification task.
So any question here?
So does the fact that we drop
all the output embeddings, apart
from the CLS token, make sense?
Yeah, yep.
Yeah, so the question is, what
does this FFN, is that right?
What does this
FFN correspond to?
So basically you have a
map between the dimension
of the output embedding
and your task of interest.
So it might be classification
of either positive or negative.
So you have some hidden
layer with some length.
So you have typically
two matrices
to learn the projection from one
to that hidden layer, and then
the hidden layer to the output.
And then you learn
these weights in order
to do the classification
task, based on the embeddings
that it has learned here.
Yeah, great question.
So that was the question
I was waiting for.
So the question is, why
do we throw away all
these other output embeddings?
So we don't need them here.
So we are in a
classification task.
We have put as convention to
operate on top of some token,
like the CLS token.
And then the magic
of this token is
that all these self-attention
mechanisms that
are in the encoder has mixed
the representation of each
of the other tokens in
that representation, such
that the output embeddings,
they are context-aware.
So basically, it's
an embedding that is
geared towards classification.
And this is what we
say will be what we
plug in to that linear layer.
And so when I say we throw
out all the other embeddings,
it's actually
something that we do
for the case of classification.
But if we do classification
at the token level,
then each of them may be used.
So for example, when I say
question answering, if you want
to detect whether a given token
is the beginning of an answer,
beginning of end
of an answer, you
would typically
have two FFNs that
respectively predict the
start and end of the answer.
And you would apply it on
each of these embeddings.
Any other questions?
Yep.
So the question is, what is
query, key, and value for CLS?
So it's going to be the same
process as all the other tokens.
So you learn here
a representation
for the embedding,
for the token CLS.
It gets projected to query.
It gets projected to key.
It gets projected to value.
It does all its
attention computation.
And at the end, you
get this embedding
that basically that has
attended to all the other ones.
So it's like the answer
is, it's the same as
for the other tokens.
So, yeah.
So just treat it as one
token, it could be any token,
and it's the same.
OK, awesome.
So I see we have
five more minutes.
And I'm going to quickly
go through the end of it.
And one thing that
was great with BERT,
and it was also
great with ELMo, is
that you have embeddings
that are contextual.
And here you can see
that it's very easy
to learn any classification
task that you want,
based on these learn embeddings.
So this is a flexibility that
was greatly appreciated here.
And it's widely used
in the industry.
So anything that comes
with sentiment detection
or other
classification-related tasks,
it's very common to use a
BERT-like model nowadays.
And I'm going to talk a bit
about its limitations now.
So as you see in
the original paper,
I think the context
length was of size 512.
So it was typically limited
in this early paper.
Afshine has mentioned
of techniques
as to how we can further
grow this context
size without making the
complexity go completely,
basically like hike.
And then you have some
approximation methods
where you compute local
attention, and so on.
And then the use of
these tricks helps
you grow the size of the
context while staying
within reasonable computation
requirement bounds.
And I'm going to talk
about two other limitations
that we're going to see what
other models try to remedy.
So there is one where the
latency could be seen as high.
You have a still 110 million
parameters for a BERT base,
so it's quite a lot.
Is there a way to make
this smaller and faster?
And then the second
one is basically
you have these two objective
functions of MLM and NSP.
Are those two truly helpful?
Is there any way we can simplify
the pre-training process?
So we're going to
see in a second how.
So first, regarding this
second limitation that we had,
this basically
sensitivity to cost.
So who here has heard
of distillation?
Good, few people.
So I just want to
flash this quote
from Hinton, Vinyals,
and Jeff Dean, which
I think has been informative.
And it's a good
mindset to have to see
that the distribution that
is output by a given model
is actually super helpful
to know what it has learned.
So the soft targets contain
almost all the knowledge.
So it's some lecture from
them that contain this quote.
So basically they were at
the origin of the concept
of distillation later on.
And you quickly see in practice
that basically learning
the distribution of a model
is more helpful than directly
learning the hard labels.
So you have this concept of
teacher and student models,
where basically the
goal in distillation
is going to be to map this
output distribution of a smaller
model directly to your
more complex model,
rather than the hard labels.
And the objective
function that you
use for this to minimize this
is the KL divergence, which
basically says in a world that
is described by the teacher,
the teacher T, how bad is it
to model with the student S.
So it basically tries to
assess how close the student
distribution is going
to be to the world's T.
And one interesting note
that you will see here
is that you find the
cross-entropy loss
if your yT distribution
is just a hard label.
So if you have just
a 1 at one position
and then 0 everywhere
else, you have
minus log of yS, which
is very interesting.
And then what the
DistilBERT folks have done--
so by the way, it's
a very clean paper,
it's like four pages,
but super impactful.
So it says that if you reduce
the number of layers by 2,
you have a lot of gains and
almost the same performance,
which is very remarkable.
And they basically used
distillation as a way
to retain that performance.
So this has been like the
key, alongside diminishing
the number of layers.
And last, I'm going
to talk about RoBERTa.
That studied the fact that
removing the NSP objective
function led to no decrease
in performance almost.
So they just dropped it.
And they added some tricks,
such as dynamically doing
the masking.
So for example, for a
given piece of text,
at each epoch, so every time
you see the same kind of text,
you would change the masking.
And they also had
some data strategy
where they saw that the model
was vastly undertrained.
So they increased the diversity
and the size of the data lot.
And they saw that benchmark
performance increased quite
a bit on the same benchmarks.
And that's it for today.
Thank you, everyone.
Have a great weekend.